(gentle ominous music)
- [Instructor] Let us
now discuss other factors
that also influence the budget constraint
or changes in the budget constraint.
One of them is taxes.
We will start with ad valorem taxes.
In ad valorem taxes, we pay us taxes,
a percentage of the value we
pay per unit of this product
or service that we are purchasing.
Let's say for example, an
example where we buy a meal.
Let's say, before tax, the meal is $10.
If the tax, ad valorem
in this case, is 5%,
it's going to be 5% of
the value of that meal.
Therefore, the after tax payment
that the consumer will need to make
will be $10 plus 5% of $10,
which in total is $10.5.
These $10.5 come from $10
plus, sorry, times one
plus the 0.5.
Sorry, 0.05 of the $10
that correspond to the tax.
And that will again become $10.5.
That is that the general expression
for an after tax payment
per unit of the good
would take this form, will be one plus tax
times the initial price.
If the tax is 10%,
that means that the
proportion is gonna be .1.
If the tax is 5%,
that means that this
proportion is going to be 0.05
and so on.
But how does that change
the budget constraint?
Well, that is that instead of P1 or P2,
we're going to have an
after tax price per unit.
That is, let's suppose, first
that only good one is taxed.
Okay?
Then the budget line will
become price times one
plus the tax times X1.
Sorry, that's price of one.
Plus, as before, just P2X2 equals income.
Okay?
If instead both X1 and X2 are taxed,
the budget line will become now similar,
but taxes will be now
imposed in both sides.
In terms of the graph of
the budget constraint,
we will see that with taxes,
the intercepts will change
as in the follow will figure.
Suppose this is the budget,
that is this is the current budget line.
For this to be the current budget line,
we would have and divided by P1 here
and M divided divide P2 here.
If there is a tax on good one,
the new budget line will
be something like this.
That is taxes, in this
case, are equivalent
to increasing the price of good one.
If instead both goods are taxed,
what we have would be that
both intercepts will decrease
and therefore the new
budget line will, sorry,
will look something like this.
That is the budget
constraint or the budget line
will shift inwards in a parallel manner
because both intercepts are changing
by the same factor, in
this case, reducing it.
Another factor that can
change the budget line
is whether we receive or the
consumer receives or not gifts.
Okay?
So a gift can come from, of course, anyone
and in some cases, the gift
will be such that we can sell it
or in other cases, we
cannot sell the gift.
So let's think first what would happen
if we cannot sell the gift.
Let us explain this with one example.
Suppose we have a food
stamp program, okay?
Okay.
And let's assume that income is 400
and the price, there are two goods.
There is food.
We're gonna call price
of food equals to $1.
And there is price of other goods.
We're gonna just call them G,
which is going to be also $1.
Okay, so $1 for goods and $1 for food.
Just to make things simple.
So let's see how this
initial budget constraint
would look like.
Well, we have learned that we would have,
let's say, food is here
and other goods are here,
then the intercepts would
be 400 divided by one,
which is 400, and 400 divided
by one, which is also 400
for food access and good
access respectively.
So for example, this could
be depicted like this
where here we have 400
and here we have 400.
Okay?
Imagine now that there is
a gift of or a food stamp
or a coupon, we're gonna
call it a food stamp coupon
equals to 200 units of food.
Okay?
So this is food.
So we need to ask what would
be the new budget line?
And the new budget line,
we're gonna depict it with green.
New budget line.
Okay.
So graphically, this is how
that situation looks like.
First, we need to ask ourselves
If I am consuming some point,
let's say, I am consuming, for example,
this point here, okay, this
might be the point 200 food,
200 units of other goods, okay?
Once I have to this point is affordable
with the original budget line,
that means that I can afford,
I can purchase and consume.
That point, we're gonna call it point A,
without the food stamp program coupon
and only with the income at the prices
that I had originally
faced, which is one and one.
So if I can purchase that bundle A,
200, 200 in that original situation,
that implies that I could
buy the same bundle now
and add it on the food
dimension, on the food access
or along the food access, 200 more,
because I have a coupon
of 200 units of food.
That is, I would be
able to consume point B,
which is 400 units of food
and 200 units of order goods.
But the same logic apply
literally to any point.
So to any point on the
original budget line.
There is another point
in the new budget line,
which is just found by adding 200 units
that are coming from the coupon.
So following that logic, I can...
By the way,
this point is hopefully
most likely actually there.
So this can be, yeah, okay.
So let's see.
The new body line is going
to be something like this
and it's going to go all the
way to a point like this.
So yeah, I was right.
This point was one.
Slightly one to the right
was the correct one.
So in this new budget line,
we have taken the original one
and we have added information
that what or which order bundles
we are also able to afford
because we have 200 units from
the food stamp coupon, okay?
So interestingly, the
set of affordable bundles
used to be something
that would look like this
in the beginning, right?
And now, it became something that looks
that added all this area here.
All this area was added
and now it looks like this.
So we have more affordable bundles.
This is would be the impact of a gift,
in this case, a food stamp
program on the budget line,
on the budget constraint.
Before we conclude the
discussion of the budget line
and the budget constraint,
I want to recommend you try to draw
and do the math of
other interesting cases.
So the first interesting case
that you should check at home is the case
in which you are able
to sell the gift, okay?
And I'll give you the hint.
So the same example of the food stamp,
I'm gonna go back to it,
where you can actually sell the coupons.
The food will yield,
will give us a different body constraint.
It's gonna become equivalent
to increasing your income.
Okay?
So to summarize, if you have a gift
like a food stamp program
that you cannot sell,
then the budget line will look
like the one with drew here.
But if you have a food stamp
or a gift that you can sell,
that thing becomes equivalent
to increasing your income.
So do the same example
but this time, assuming that
people can sell the coupons
and try to do the same
drawing with this new thing
that coupons can be sold and
you will see a difference.
Okay?
So that is one task or
homework, if you want.
Another one I recommend you do
is to think about the following.
What happens with the budget line
if we have a price that lowers
if you buy many enough
units of something, right?
So there are some places
and some marketplaces that tells you
if you buy the first 10
units, you pay whatever,
$100 per unit.
But if you buy more than 10 units,
you might pay only $80 per unit, right?
So it's a decrease in price
that comes if you buy in bulk or volume.
But in other markets,
you will find sort of the opposite, right?
To encourage you to
buy at least something,
they will tell you you
can pay a lower price
for the first five units
you buy of something.
For the first five meals,
you pay this lower price
and for the next units,
you pay more, right?
So that is the opposite in the sense
that now the price is
lower for the first units
and higher for the additional units.
Okay.
So think about those cases
and do the math about those.
For now, the hints for each
of them are as follows, okay?
This is your homework, okay?
Separate from the official
homework that you would turn in.
This is for homework not to turn in.
And first one is lower price
if purchase in bulk, right?
And so you can do an
(faintly speaking) example,
but I'm just gonna do the graph here
on how the budget line looks.
And it's gonna look like this.
So suppose the discount for
buying in bulk applies to X1.
So you're gonna pay a
price up to some point,
let's say, this point.
But then if you buy more
than this threshold,
you pay a lower price.
So the slope must become flatter, right?
Because that's what happens
when the price is lower.
So this would be the how
the budget line will look
when you have a discount
for buying in bulk,
a discount per unit, right?
Lower price for in higher amounts of X1.
Now, let's do this similar thing.
If you have actually a discount.
A discount for the first 10
units, for example, okay.
This is, for example,
discount for 10 units.
So in the case of discount
for the first 10 units,
again, of X1, we will have the following.
So now the first 10 units
are going to be cheaper,
meaning the budget line will
be flatter for those 10 units.
And then it's going to become steeper
'cause the normal price will kick in.
So it's gonna go something like this
because cheaper for the first 10 units,
and then it's gonna be like this.
Okay?
And this would be the 10 units
that I was mentioning, okay?
This is the discount
for the first 10 units.
Okay.
Well, with this hints for
you to solve this problems
at home, we will conclude
this chapter or this section
and move on to the next one.
I'll see you very soon.
(gentle ominous music)